Updated: Jun 18, 2021

Marta Karas

Contact Information 615 N Wolfe St Rm E3039 Baltimore, MD 21205

USA

Phone: +1 (317) 665-4551

E-mail: marta.karass@gmail.com Web: https://martakarass.github.io/

Profile

5-th year PhD candidate in Biostatistics at Johns Hopkins University (exp. graduation Dec 2021).

STATISTICAL METHODS interests: methods for processing, features extraction and analysis of accelerometry data (both subsecond-level and summary measures), causal inference (single-subject trials; non-experimental settings; time-varying exposures), GAMs, functional regression models, machine learning, R software development.

SCIENTIFIC RESEARCH interests: wearable devices and their applications in epidemiological and clinical studies.

EDUCATION

Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD, USA

Ph.D., Biostatistics, Aug 2017 – (Exp.) Dec 2021

• Academic Advisors: Ciprian M. Crainiceanu, Jacek K. Urbanek

Wroclaw University of Science and Technology, Wroclaw, Poland

M.S., Mathematics (Mathematical Statistics), Jul 2015

- Dissertation: "Theoretical and practical issues in change point detection." (Thesis link)
- Academic Advisor: Malgorzata Bogdan
- Final grade: 5.5/5.5 (Excellent). Graduation with Academic Distinction

Wroclaw University of Science and Technology, Wroclaw, Poland

B.S., Mathematics, Jun 2013

• Final grade: 5.0/5.5 (Very good)

Industry EXPERIENCE

Evidation Health (Digital Health), San Mateo, CA, USA

Data Science Intern

Jun 2019 - Aug 2019

- Designed, performed, and reported analysis to estimate post-surgery recovery trajectories and predict recovery time from wearable patient-generated health data (research article published).
- Proposed and implemented an extension of the existing methodology for measuring sedentary/active accumulation time.

Novartis (Pharmaceutical), Basel, Switzerland

Sensor Data Analytic Intern

Jun 2019 - Aug 2019

- Proposed, implemented, and evaluated a method for free-living walking strides segmentation from wrist-worn accelerometry sensor (research article published).
- Quantified association between walking features and PROs in a diseased population.

Opera Software (Software, Web Browser), Wroclaw, Poland

Analyst (full-time)

Aug 2016 - Dec 2016, Jul 2015 - Dec 2015

- Designed and implemented methodology for A/B-test results analysis.
- Developed time-series forecasting models for Opera browser's KPIs.
- Performed ad hoc user base analysis for software product improvements.
- Designed and implemented a Bayesian framework for inference about users' behavior.

Datarino (Big Data Services & Data Management Solutions), Wroclaw, Poland

Data Scientist (part-time)

Jul 2014 - Mar 2015

- Performed ad hoc analysis of user base and monetization KPIs of Polish social network service.
- Performed analyses of business partners' big-data size data sets.

ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

Johns Hopkins University, Department of Biostatistics, Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD, USA

Research Assistant

Jan 2018 - present

Work in progress:

- Proposing and implementing a method for estimating the causal effect of time-varying exposure in a single-subject observational study with repeated outcomes.
- Evaluating novel resampling method for estimating statistical test power sample size in complex modeling settings, including multilevel data problems.

Completed work:

- Performed extensive literature review on raw accelerometry data usage in health research.
- Developed and evaluated a method for pattern segmentation from raw accelerometry data.
- Proposed, implemented and evaluated a method for high-specificity identification of walking from wrist-worn accelerometry data collected in free-living.
- Designed, performed and reported analysis of large (n=600+) cohort study to develop pair-wise transformations of minute-level actigraphy-derived measures.
- Designed and conducted small studies to collect raw accelerometry data in free-living with semisupervised exercise components.
- Developed open-source software (R packages) scoring a total of 2500+ CRAN downloads/month.

Indiana University Bloomington, Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, School of Public Health, Bloomington, IN, USA

Research Assistant

Jan 2017 - Jul 2017

• Applied graph-constrained regularization methods to quantify the association between brain structural imaging markers and HIV+/HIV- status.

Indiana University – Purdue University Indianapolis, Department of Biostatistics, Richard M. Fairbanks School of Public Health, Indianapolis, IN, USA

Research Assistant

Jan 2016 - Jul 2016

- Proposed, implemented and evaluated extension of existing graph-constrained regularization methods for linear regression.
- Quantified association between brain structural imaging markers and alcohol abuse.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Johns Hopkins University, Department of Biostatistics, Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD, USA

Instructor

- 2021-22 Summer Institute 140.604 Introduction to R for Public Health Researchers
- 2019-20 Term 1 140.850 Special topics course: Biostatistical Methods for Wearable Computing

Teaching assistant

- 2020-21 Term 2 140.651 Methods in Biostatistics II. (Lead TA)
- 2020-21 Term 1 140.651 Methods in Biostatistics I. (Lead TA)
- 2019-20 Term 2 140.652 Methods in Biostatistics II. (Lead TA)
- 2019-20 Term 1 140.651 Methods in Biostatistics I. (Lead TA)
- 2018-19 Term 4 140.624 Statistical Methods in Public Health IV.
- 2018-19 Term 3 140.623 Statistical Methods in Public Health III.
- 2018-19 Term 2 140.652 Methods in Biostatistics II.
- 2018-19 Term 1 140.651 Methods in Biostatistics I.

Honors and Awards

- 1. Louis I. and Thomas D. Dublin Award for the Advancement of Epidemiology and Biostatistics. Johns Hopkins University, Department of Biostatistics and Department of Epidemiology. 2021 (link)
- 2. Helen Abbey Award for Excellence in Teaching. Johns Hopkins University, Department of Biostatistics. $2021 \ (link)$
- 3. Leadership, Empowerment and Learning Culture Award. Novartis US Analytics Conference. $2019\,$
- 4. ENAR Poster Award. ENAR. 2017

Professional Activities

- Referee for: PLOS ONE, Digital Biomarkers. (Publons profile link)
- JHU Biostatistics Student Organization service: International Students Affairs Committee chair.

PUBLICATIONS

- 1. **Karas, M.**, Urbanek, J.K., Illiano, V.P., Bogaarts, G., Crainiceanu, C.M., Dorn, J.F. (2021). Estimation of free-living walking cadence from wrist-worn sensor accelerometry data and its association with SF-36 quality of life scores, Physiological Measurement, Online ahead of print. (Article link)
- 2. Brzyski, D., Karas, M., Ances, B., Dzemidzic, M., Goni, J., Randolph, T.W., Harezlak, J. (2021). Connectivity-Informed Adaptive Regularization for Generalized Outcomes, The Canadian Journal of Statistics.
- 3. Karas, M., Marinsek, N., Goldhahn, J., Foschini, L., Ramirez, E., Clay, I. (2020). Predicting subjective recovery from lower limb surgery using consumer wearables, Digital Biomarkers, 4(suppl 1):73-86. (Article link)
- 4. Karas, M., Straczkiewicz, M., Fadel, W., Harezlak, J., Crainiceanu, C.M., Urbanek, J.K. (2018). Adaptive empirical pattern transformation (ADEPT) with application to walking stride segmentation, Biostatistics, kxz033. (Article link)

- 5. Karas, M., Bai, J., Straczkiewicz, M., Harezlak, J., Glynn, N.W., Harris, T., Zipunnikov, V., Crainiceanu, C.M., Urbanek, J.K. (2019). Accelerometry data in health research: challenges and opportunities. Statistics in Biosciences, 11(2), 210237. (Article link)
- 6. Karas, M., Brzyski, D., Dzemidzic, M., Goni, J., Kareken, D.A., Randolph, T., Harezlak, J. (2019). Brain connectivity-informed regularization methods for regression. Statistics in Biosciences, 11(1), 47-90. (Article link)

Conference Posters

- 1. Karas, M., Brzyski, D., Ances, B., Goni, J., Randolph, T.W., Harezlak, J. Association of Structural Brain Imaging Measures with HIV Markers Incorporating Structural Connectivity Information: a Regularized Statistical Approach. ENAR, Washington DC, USA, Mar 2017. (Received ENAR Poster Award).
- 2. Karas, M. Penalized regression inference regarding variable selection in high dimensions: presentation of selected methods implemented in R. European R Users Conference, Poznan, Poland, Oct 2016.

Talks

- Conference/Invited 1. Karas, M., Dorn, J., Urbanek, J.K. Estimation of free-living walking cadence from wrist-worn sensor accelerometry data and its association with SF-36 quality of life scores. ENAR 2021, virtual conference, Mar 2021.
 - 2. Karas, M., Dorn, J., Urbanek, J.K. Estimation of free-living walking cadence from wrist-worn sensor accelerometry data and its association with SF-36 quality of life scores. CMStatistics 2020, virtual conference, Dec 2020.
 - 3. Karas, M., Dorn, J., Urbanek, J.K. Novel approach for precise walking cadence estimation from high-density tri-axial accelerometry data collected at wrist in free-living. 41st Annual Conference of the International Society for Clinical Biostatistics, virtual conference, Aug 2020.
 - 4. Karas, M., Roemmich, R., Bastian, A., Urbanek, J.K. Urbanek, Crainiceanu, C.M. Functional registration of walking strides in high-density accelerometry data for estimation of gait asymmetry. CFE-CMStatistics 2019 conference, London, UK, Dec 2019.
 - 5. Karas, M., Dorn, J. Walking measurements derived from free-living wrist-worn sensor as novel digital endpoints. Novartis 2019 US Analytics Conference, East Hanover, NJ, USA, Oct 2019.
 - 6. Karas, M., Roemmich, R., Crainiceanu, C.M., Bastian, A., Urbanek, J.K. Automatic estimation of step asymmetry from accelerometry data. ICAMPAM 2019, Maastricht, The Netherlands, Jul 2019.
 - 7. Karas, M., Harezlak, J., Straczkiewicz, M., Fadel, W., Crainiceanu, C.M., Urbanek, J.K. ADaptive Empirical Pattern Transformation (ADEPT) with application to walking stride seqmentation. JSM 2018, Vancouver, Canada, Aug 2018.
 - 8. Karas, M.. Wearable accelerometers, accelerometry data and automatic steps segmentation in R: strideter and convo R packages. Why R? 2018 Conference, Wroclaw, Poland, Jul 2018.

SOFTWARE SEVELOPMENT

- 1. arctools R package: Processing and Physical Activity Summaries of Minute Level Activity Data *GitHub*)
- 2. adept R package: Adaptive Empirical Pattern Transformation. (CRAN, GitHub, website). (Selected in Top 40 new CRAN packages in May 2019; list link)
- 3. adeptdata R package: Accelerometry Data Sets. (CRAN, GitHub)
- 4. runstats R package: Fast Computation of Running Statistics for Time Series. (CRAN, GitHub, website)
- 5. mdpeer R package: Graph-Constrained Regression with Enhanced Regularization Parameters Selection. (CRAN)

COMPUTER SKILLS • R, Python, Git.